<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>One Apostolic Catholic</title><link>https://example.com/</link><description>Sharing Catholic Teachings.</description><atom:link href="https://example.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:ancientla68@gmail.com"&gt;One Catholic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 06:48:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Baptism: born of Water and Spirit.</title><link>https://example.com/posts/born-of-water/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baptism: Born of Water and Spirit&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the sacrament that washes away original sin and makes us children of God. Through it, we are initiated into the Church and begin the journey of Christian life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus commanded His disciples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit.” (Matthew 28:19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Baptism, we are spiritually reborn, receiving grace to live a holy life. Infants and adults alike are welcomed into God’s family, showing that salvation is a gift from Him, not earned by human understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some misunderstandings exist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s just symbolic.” — Baptism truly cleanses the soul from sin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Infants shouldn’t be baptized.” — God’s grace is for all; Christ welcomed children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Faith alone is enough.” — Faith is essential, but Baptism is the ordinary means of entering God’s kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the beginning of a lifelong relationship with Christ. It unites us to His Church, marks us permanently as God’s children, and opens the door to all other sacraments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.” (John 3:5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Receiving Baptism is more than a ritual — it is a divine rebirth and the first step into the grace-filled life God calls us to.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/born-of-water/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 07:02:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Euchariat: Our spiritual Nourishment.</title><link>https://example.com/posts/the-euchariat-our-spiritual-nourishment/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Eucharist: Our Spiritual Nourishment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eucharist is the sacrament in which Jesus Christ is truly present — Body, Blood, Soul, and Divinity — under the appearances of bread and wine. It is the heart of Catholic life, called the source and summit of Christian life (CCC 1324).
.. TEASER_END
Jesus Himself instituted the Eucharist at the Last Supper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Take, eat; this is my body… Drink of it, all of you; this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins.” (Matthew 26:26–28)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By receiving the Eucharist, we are united with Christ in a unique and powerful way. It strengthens us to live holy lives, forgives our venial sins, and nourishes our souls like spiritual food. The Eucharist also unites all who partake into one Body — the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some misunderstandings exist about this sacrament:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s just symbolic.” — Catholics believe in transubstantiation, that the bread and wine truly become Christ’s Body and Blood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Any Christian can receive it.” — Only baptized Catholics in a state of grace may receive, to preserve the unity and sanctity of the sacrament.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Prayer alone is enough.” — While prayer is vital, the Eucharist is a sacramental encounter with Christ Himself that nourishes the soul in a way personal prayer cannot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Receiving the Eucharist is not just an act of devotion — it is a participation in the sacrifice of Christ, a foretaste of heaven, and a source of grace to live faithfully each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life.” (John 6:54)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eucharist invites us into a deep communion with Jesus, strengthens our faith, and empowers us to share His love with the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/the-euchariat-our-spiritual-nourishment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:57:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sacrament of the Eucharist: The source and summit of Christian life</title><link>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-the-eucharist-the-source-and-summit-of-christian-life/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Sacrament of the Eucharist: The Source and Summit of Christian Life
.. TEASER_END
What the Eucharist Is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eucharist, also called Holy Communion, is the sacrament in which Jesus Christ is truly present — Body, Blood, Soul, and Divinity — under the appearances of bread and wine. It is the source and summit of the Christian life, because it nourishes the soul, unites believers with Christ, and strengthens the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the Eucharist, Catholics participate in Christ’s sacrifice on the Cross in an unbloody and sacramental manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical Foundation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Last Supper: “Take, eat; this is my body… Drink of it, all of you; this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many for the forgiveness of sins.” (Matthew 26:26–28)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul’s Teaching: “For as often as you eat this bread and drink the cup, you proclaim the Lord’s death until he comes.” (1 Corinthians 11:26)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ commanded His disciples to continue celebrating this sacrament, giving the Church a way to remain spiritually united with Him throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Effects of the Eucharist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Union with Christ: The faithful are intimately united with Jesus’ Body and Blood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness of venial sins: The Eucharist cleanses the soul and strengthens against temptation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spiritual nourishment: It sustains the soul, helping believers live holy lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unity of the Church: Those who receive the Eucharist become one Body in Christ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church teaches:
“The Eucharist is the source and summit of the Christian life. The other sacraments, and indeed all ecclesiastical ministries and works of the apostolate, are bound up with the Eucharist and are oriented toward it.” (CCC 1324)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Misunderstandings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s just symbolic.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: The Eucharist is not a mere symbol. Through transubstantiation, the bread and wine truly become Christ’s Body and Blood, even though the appearances of bread and wine remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Any Christian can receive it.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Only baptized Catholics in a state of grace may receive the Eucharist, because it is a sacrament of unity and profound communion with Christ and His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s unnecessary; prayer is enough.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Prayer is vital, but the Eucharist is a unique sacramental encounter with Christ that strengthens the soul in ways that personal prayer alone cannot provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eucharist is the heart of Catholic life. It is a living memorial of Christ’s sacrifice, a foretaste of heaven, and the source of grace for living as His disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Whoever eats my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life, and I will raise him on the last day.” (John 6:54)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By receiving the Eucharist, Catholics are drawn into the mystery of Christ’s love, nourished spiritually, and empowered to live lives of holiness and charity.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-the-eucharist-the-source-and-summit-of-christian-life/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:53:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Seven sacraments of the catholic church</title><link>https://example.com/posts/the-Seven-sacraments-of-the-catholic-church/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Seven Sacraments of the Catholic Church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church teaches that there are seven sacraments, instituted by Jesus Christ, through which divine grace is conferred to the faithful. These sacraments are visible signs of God’s invisible action in our lives, guiding us toward holiness and eternal life.
.. TEASER_END&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Baptism&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament that cleanses a person from original sin, initiates them into the Church, and makes them a child of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: John 3:5; Matthew 28:19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Forgiveness of sins, new life in Christ, entry into the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Confirmation (Chrismation)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament in which a baptized person receives the Holy Spirit to strengthen their faith and witness to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: Acts 8:14–17; Acts 19:6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Full outpouring of the Holy Spirit, strengthening of Christian life, and growth in virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eucharist&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament of Christ’s Body and Blood, received in Holy Communion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: Luke 22:19–20; 1 Corinthians 11:23–26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Union with Christ, spiritual nourishment, and participation in His sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Penance (Confession/Reconciliation)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament in which sins committed after Baptism are forgiven through the priest’s absolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: John 20:22–23; James 5:16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Forgiveness of sins, reconciliation with God and the Church, spiritual healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anointing of the Sick&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament of healing for those who are seriously ill, elderly, or near death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: James 5:14–15; Mark 6:13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Spiritual and sometimes physical healing, courage, and union with Christ’s suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Holy Orders&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament by which men are ordained as deacons, priests, or bishops to serve the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: Acts 6:5–6; 1 Timothy 4:14; Luke 22:19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Grace to teach, sanctify, and govern in the Church; configuration to Christ the High Priest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Matrimony (Marriage)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it is: The sacrament in which a man and a woman enter a lifelong covenant of love, fidelity, and openness to children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical basis: Genesis 2:24; Matthew 19:4–6; Ephesians 5:25–32.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effect: Grace for mutual love, faithfulness, and cooperation with God in raising a family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seven sacraments are the pillars of Catholic spiritual life. Each sacrament is a gift from God, giving grace to help the faithful grow in holiness, remain close to Christ, and participate fully in the life of the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Sacraments are efficacious signs of grace, instituted by Christ and entrusted to the Church, by which divine life is dispensed to us.” (Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1131)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/the-Seven-sacraments-of-the-catholic-church/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:50:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sacrament of Marriage: A covenant of Grace and Love</title><link>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-marriage-a-covenant-of-grace-and-love/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Sacrament of Marriage: A Covenant of Love and Grace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Marriage Is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Catholic Church, Marriage is a sacred covenant between a man and a woman, instituted by God, through which the couple loves, supports, and cooperates with God’s plan for family and society. It is a sacrament because Christ Himself is present in the marriage, granting grace to help spouses remain faithful and love one another selflessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Church teaches that marriage is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Permanent – “What God has joined, no one must separate” (Mark 10:9).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exclusive – between one man and one woman.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open to life – the couple cooperates with God in bringing new life into the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical Foundation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genesis 2:24 – “Therefore a man leaves his father and mother and clings to his wife, and they become one flesh.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 19:4–6 – Jesus confirms the divine plan for marriage, emphasizing its permanence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephesians 5:25–32 – St. Paul compares the love between husband and wife to Christ’s love for the Church, showing that marriage is a reflection of divine love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Graces of the Sacrament&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the sacrament of marriage, spouses receive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sanctifying grace – to live their vows faithfully.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strength for mutual love – to forgive, support, and grow together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cooperation with God in parenthood – to nurture and educate children in the faith.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marriage is not only a human commitment but also a vocation — a calling to holiness through love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Misunderstandings and Catholic Responses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Marriage is just a legal contract.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: While marriage has legal aspects, the sacrament is primarily a spiritual covenant, blessed by God, and a means of grace for the couple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Marriage can be easily broken; divorce is acceptable.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: The Church teaches that a valid sacramental marriage is indissoluble. Civil divorce does not dissolve the sacramental bond. Only a declaration of nullity (annulment) can recognize that a true sacramental marriage never existed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Marriage is just about love; children aren’t necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Marriage is both unitive and procreative. Love strengthens the bond between spouses, and openness to children fulfills God’s plan for family and society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marriage in the Catholic Church is much more than a ceremony — it is a sacrament of grace that mirrors Christ’s love for His Church. It calls spouses to holiness, selfless love, and cooperation with God in the gift of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Husbands, love your wives, as Christ loved the Church and gave Himself up for her.” (Ephesians 5:25)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By embracing the sacramental graces, couples can build strong, holy marriages that reflect God’s love in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-marriage-a-covenant-of-grace-and-love/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:46:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sacrament of Anointing of the sick: God's healing and comfort</title><link>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-anointing-of-the-sick-gods-healing-and-comfort/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Sacrament of the Anointing of the Sick: God’s Healing and Comfort
.. TEASER_END
What the Sacrament Is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anointing of the Sick is a sacrament through which God heals, strengthens, and comforts those who are seriously ill, elderly, or facing major health challenges. It was instituted by Christ to bring the faithful closer to Him in suffering and to unite their pain with His redemptive love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sacrament is not only for the dying — it is for anyone facing serious illness or surgery, helping them spiritually and sometimes even physically through God’s grace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical Foundation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James 5:14–15 — “Is anyone among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord. And the prayer of faith will save the one who is sick, and the Lord will raise him up; and if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark 6:13 — The Apostles anointed the sick and healed them in Christ’s name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These passages show that Christ gave His Church the authority to bring healing through prayer and sacramental anointing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How the Sacrament Works&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priest anoints the forehead and hands of the sick person with holy oil, usually called the Oil of the Sick, while praying for God’s mercy, forgiveness, and healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sacrament provides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spiritual healing — forgiveness of sins if the person is contrite.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strength and courage — to endure suffering with faith.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Union with Christ’s suffering — offering one’s trials for the salvation of souls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Physical healing — if God wills, the body may also be healed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Misunderstandings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s only for people who are about to die.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: While it can prepare the dying for eternal life, the sacrament is for anyone seriously ill or weakened by old age (CCC 1514). Receiving it earlier allows one to unite suffering with Christ before the end of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“It’s just symbolic; it doesn’t actually help.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Like all sacraments, Anointing is a means of grace instituted by Christ. The oil and prayers are outward signs of God’s invisible healing and strengthening power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I can pray at home; I don’t need a priest.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Prayer is important, but the Church, through Christ, gives the priest the authority to anoint in His name. This sacramental action conveys grace in a unique and powerful way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anointing of the Sick is a beautiful sacrament of God’s love, mercy, and presence in our weakness. It reminds us that Christ is with us in suffering and that no pain is meaningless when united to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest.” (Matthew 11:28)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By receiving this sacrament, the faithful are not only comforted and strengthened, but their suffering becomes a participation in Christ’s redemptive work, bringing grace to themselves and to the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-anointing-of-the-sick-gods-healing-and-comfort/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:42:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sacrament of Holy Orders: Serving Christ and his Church</title><link>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-holy-orders-serving-christ-and-his-church/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Sacrament of Holy Orders: Serving Christ and His Church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Holy Orders Is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sacrament of Holy Orders is the sacrament through which the mission entrusted by Christ to His Apostles continues in the Church. Through this sacrament, men are ordained as deacons, priests, or bishops, enabling them to serve the Church in teaching, sanctifying, and governing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy Orders is a sacrament of service, not personal status. It is a permanent spiritual character (called an “indelible mark”) that configures the ordained to Christ, the eternal High Priest, to carry out His mission on earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical Foundation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew 28:19–20 — Jesus commands His Apostles: “Go therefore and make disciples of all nations…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 22:19–20 — At the Last Supper, Christ institutes the priesthood through the Eucharist: “Do this in remembrance of me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 6:5–6 — The Apostles lay hands on deacons to serve the community, showing the early Church’s practice of ordination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Timothy 4:14 — Paul reminds Timothy: “Do not neglect the gift that is in you, which was given to you through prophecy with the laying on of hands of the presbyterate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These passages show that Christ instituted a ministerial hierarchy, and the Church continues it through Holy Orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levels of Holy Orders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deacon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serves the Church in charity, liturgy, and the Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can baptize, witness marriages, and preach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Priest&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts in persona Christi (in the person of Christ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Celebrates the Eucharist, absolves sins in Confession, anoints the sick, and teaches the faithful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bishop&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Receives the fullness of Holy Orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oversees a diocese, ordains priests and deacons, and maintains apostolic succession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose and Spiritual Effects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Holy Orders, the ordained receive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grace to act in Christ’s name for the salvation of souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spiritual character that cannot be repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authority to teach, sanctify, and govern in the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church teaches:
“Holy Orders makes the bishop, priest, or deacon capable of acting in the person of Christ the Head. It configures him to Christ in a unique way, allowing him to serve the faithful in love and truth.” (CCC 1536)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Misunderstandings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Holy Orders is just a job, not a sacrament.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: It is a sacrament instituted by Christ, not merely a role. The grace conferred transforms the soul permanently, unlike a temporary ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Anyone can minister; we don’t need priests or bishops.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Christ gave authority to the Apostles and their successors. While the laity participates in the Church’s mission, the ordained act in persona Christi, uniquely mediating the sacraments for the faithful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Women should be ordained too.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: The Church follows Christ’s example and Apostolic tradition: only men are ordained, as consistently taught by the Magisterium (CCC 1577).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy Orders is a sacrament of service, authority, and grace. It ensures that the Church has shepherds, teachers, and ministers who can guide the faithful, celebrate the sacraments, and continue the mission of Christ on earth. Through the ordained, Christ Himself continues to teach, sanctify, and govern His people, maintaining the apostolic mission that began with the Apostles nearly two thousand years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “The one who receives the priesthood receives the power to act in the name of Christ for the salvation of souls.”&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/sacrament-of-holy-orders-serving-christ-and-his-church/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:38:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Chrismation: The anointing of the Holy Ghost</title><link>https://example.com/posts/chrismation-the-anointing-of-the-holy-ghost/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Chrismation: The Anointing with the Holy Spirit
.. TEASER_END
What Chrismation Is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrismation is the sacrament in which a baptized person receives the gift of the Holy Spirit. It is sometimes called the “anointing” and is closely associated with Confirmation in the Western Church. In Apostolic Catholic practice, Chrismation is often administered immediately after Baptism, even for infants, as part of the initiation into the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priest or bishop anoints the baptized person with holy chrism oil, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “The seal of the gift of the Holy Spirit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this sacrament, the person is strengthened by the Holy Spirit to live as a Christian, bear witness to Christ, and grow in holiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biblical Basis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 8:14–17 — The Apostles laid hands on baptized believers to receive the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acts 19:6 — “When Paul laid his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came upon them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These passages show that the Holy Spirit was conferred sacramentally through the Church’s ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connection with Baptism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Apostolic tradition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism washes away original sin and begins the Christian life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrismation completes the initiation by imparting the Holy Spirit to strengthen the soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these sacraments unite the believer with Christ, the Church, and the gifts of the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church notes:
“By the sacrament of Confirmation [Chrismation], the baptized are more perfectly bound to the Church and are enriched with a special strength of the Holy Spirit.” (CCC 1285)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Misunderstandings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Protestant groups claim:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Holy Spirit comes automatically at Baptism; Chrismation/Confirmation isn’t necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: While Baptism brings the Holy Spirit, Chrismation confers the fullness of the Spirit’s gifts. It is a visible, sacramental strengthening for Christian life. Scripture shows the Apostles laying hands and praying for the Spirit to come (Acts 8:17), which supports the sacramental action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s just symbolic, not a real grace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Like all sacraments, Chrismation is a means of grace instituted by Christ. The Holy Spirit truly comes upon the person, empowering them to live a holy life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gifts of the Holy Spirit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Chrismation, the believer receives the seven gifts of the Holy Spirit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wisdom&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Understanding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Counsel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fortitude&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowledge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piety&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fear of the Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These gifts guide Christians to grow in virtue, love, and witness to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrismation is a profound sacrament of grace, marking the believer with the seal of the Holy Spirit. It strengthens the baptized for a life of faith, courage, and service to God and His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “But you will receive power when the Holy Spirit has come upon you; and you shall be my witnesses…” (Acts 1:8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Apostolic Catholic tradition, Baptism, Chrismation, and the Eucharist together fully initiate a person into the life of Christ and His Church.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/chrismation-the-anointing-of-the-holy-ghost/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:36:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Confession: Christ's gift of mercy through his church</title><link>https://example.com/posts/confession-christs-gift-of-mercy-through-his-church/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Confession: Christ’s Gift of Mercy Through His Church
.. TEASER_END
What the Catholic Church Teaches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession, also called the Sacrament of Penance or Reconciliation, is the sacrament by which sins committed after Baptism are forgiven. It was instituted by Jesus Christ Himself when He gave the Apostles authority to forgive sins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven them; if you retain the sins of any, they are retained.” (John 20:22–23)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church says:
“Those who approach the sacrament of Penance obtain pardon from God’s mercy for the offense committed against Him, and are at the same time reconciled with the Church.” (CCC 1422)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Confession, we are not only forgiven by God but also healed spiritually and restored to communion with the Body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why Catholics Confess to a Priest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Christians argue, “Why confess to a priest when I can go directly to God?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholics do confess directly to God — but Jesus gave His priests the authority to act as His representatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as God uses human ministers to baptize, marry, and preach, He also uses them to forgive sins sacramentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priest is not forgiving by his own power — he forgives in the name of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Protestant Objections and Catholic Responses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Only God can forgive sins.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Absolutely — only God can forgive sins. But He chooses to forgive through His priests. In John 20:22–23, Jesus gives the Apostles the authority to forgive or retain sins. If God did not intend priests to forgive, why would Christ give such power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Confession is not in the Bible.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: It is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James 5:16 — “Confess your sins to one another, and pray for one another, that you may be healed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Corinthians 5:18 — “God… gave us the ministry of reconciliation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John 20:23 — explicit authority to forgive sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the earliest centuries, Christians confessed their sins to bishops and priests — this is documented in the writings of the Church Fathers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I confess in private prayer; that’s enough.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Personal prayer is good, but Christ gave us a sacrament for certainty and grace. When the priest says, “I absolve you,” you have the assurance that your sins are truly forgiven. Without the sacrament, you rely on feelings — but with Confession, you receive a clear sacramental guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Healing Power of Confession&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession not only forgives sin but also strengthens the soul. Many Catholics testify to the peace that comes after honestly confessing and hearing the words of absolution. The sacrament brings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness of mortal and venial sins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healing of spiritual wounds caused by sin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strength against future temptation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restoration of grace and deeper union with God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession is not a human invention, but a divine gift. Jesus entrusted His Apostles and their successors with the power to forgive sins so that His mercy could reach us tangibly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far from being a burden, Confession is a channel of freedom. The sinner kneels before the priest, but truly confesses before Christ Himself, who acts through His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “If we confess our sins, He is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.” (1 John 1:9)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Confession, the Catholic encounters not judgment but mercy, not despair but hope, not death but life.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://example.com/posts/confession-christs-gift-of-mercy-through-his-church/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:33:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Baptism in the catholic church: the gateway to salvation</title><link>https://example.com/posts/baptism-in-the-catholic-church-the-gateway-to-salvation/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Baptism in the Catholic Church: The Gateway to Salvation
.. TEASER_END
What the Catholic Church Teaches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the first of the Sacraments and the gateway to the Christian life. Through it, we are freed from original sin, reborn as children of God, and incorporated into the Body of Christ, the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus Himself commanded Baptism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.” (John 3:5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And before ascending into heaven, He sent the Apostles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit.” (Matthew 28:19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the very beginning, the Apostles baptized entire households (Acts 16:15, 16:33; 1 Corinthians 1:16), showing that Baptism was never limited to adults only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church says:
“Holy Baptism is the basis of the whole Christian life, the gateway to life in the Spirit… Through Baptism we are freed from sin and reborn as sons of God; we become members of Christ, are incorporated into the Church and made sharers in her mission.” (CCC 1213)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Protestant Objections and Catholic Responses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Baptism is only symbolic; it doesn’t actually save.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Scripture clearly teaches Baptism is not mere symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Baptism… now saves you.” (1 Peter 3:21)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Rise and be baptized, and wash away your sins, calling on his name.” (Acts 22:16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is a true sacrament — an outward sign that actually confers grace. Just as water washes the body, the Holy Spirit cleanses the soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Only adults who can profess faith should be baptized; infants don’t understand.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Salvation is God’s free gift, not based on human understanding. Jesus welcomed children:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let the little children come to me, and do not hinder them, for to such belongs the kingdom of heaven.” (Matthew 19:14)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apostles baptized whole households, which surely included children (Acts 16:15, 16:33).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as circumcision brought infants into God’s covenant in the Old Testament (Genesis 17:12), Baptism brings infants into the New Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Faith alone saves; Baptism isn’t necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Faith is essential, but Jesus commanded Baptism as the ordinary means of salvation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He who believes and is baptized will be saved.” (Mark 16:16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early Church never separated faith from Baptism. To be baptized was to profess faith in Christ and enter His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is far more than a symbol. It is the sacrament instituted by Christ that washes away sin, makes us children of God, and unites us to His Church. To reject Baptism is to reject Christ’s own command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church, faithful to 2,000 years of Apostolic teaching, continues to baptize infants and adults alike, bringing souls into the life of grace that Christ promised:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.” (John 3:5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is not optional; it is the very door to salvation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>baptism</category><guid>https://example.com/posts/baptism-in-the-catholic-church-the-gateway-to-salvation/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:29:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>