<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>One Apostolic Catholic (Posts about baptism)</title><link>https://example.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://example.com/categories/baptism.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:ancientla68@gmail.com"&gt;One Catholic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 07:37:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Baptism in the catholic church: the gateway to salvation</title><link>https://example.com/posts/baptism-in-the-catholic-church-the-gateway-to-salvation/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Baptism in the Catholic Church: The Gateway to Salvation
.. TEASER_END
What the Catholic Church Teaches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the first of the Sacraments and the gateway to the Christian life. Through it, we are freed from original sin, reborn as children of God, and incorporated into the Body of Christ, the Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus Himself commanded Baptism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.” (John 3:5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And before ascending into heaven, He sent the Apostles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Go therefore and make disciples of all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit.” (Matthew 28:19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the very beginning, the Apostles baptized entire households (Acts 16:15, 16:33; 1 Corinthians 1:16), showing that Baptism was never limited to adults only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church says:
“Holy Baptism is the basis of the whole Christian life, the gateway to life in the Spirit… Through Baptism we are freed from sin and reborn as sons of God; we become members of Christ, are incorporated into the Church and made sharers in her mission.” (CCC 1213)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Protestant Objections and Catholic Responses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Baptism is only symbolic; it doesn’t actually save.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Scripture clearly teaches Baptism is not mere symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Baptism… now saves you.” (1 Peter 3:21)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Rise and be baptized, and wash away your sins, calling on his name.” (Acts 22:16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is a true sacrament — an outward sign that actually confers grace. Just as water washes the body, the Holy Spirit cleanses the soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Only adults who can profess faith should be baptized; infants don’t understand.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Salvation is God’s free gift, not based on human understanding. Jesus welcomed children:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let the little children come to me, and do not hinder them, for to such belongs the kingdom of heaven.” (Matthew 19:14)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apostles baptized whole households, which surely included children (Acts 16:15, 16:33).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as circumcision brought infants into God’s covenant in the Old Testament (Genesis 17:12), Baptism brings infants into the New Covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Faith alone saves; Baptism isn’t necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catholic Response: Faith is essential, but Jesus commanded Baptism as the ordinary means of salvation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He who believes and is baptized will be saved.” (Mark 16:16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early Church never separated faith from Baptism. To be baptized was to profess faith in Christ and enter His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;---&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is far more than a symbol. It is the sacrament instituted by Christ that washes away sin, makes us children of God, and unites us to His Church. To reject Baptism is to reject Christ’s own command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church, faithful to 2,000 years of Apostolic teaching, continues to baptize infants and adults alike, bringing souls into the life of grace that Christ promised:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; “Unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God.” (John 3:5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is not optional; it is the very door to salvation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>baptism</category><guid>https://example.com/posts/baptism-in-the-catholic-church-the-gateway-to-salvation/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:29:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>