<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>One Apostolic Catholic (Posts about pentecost)</title><link>https://example.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://example.com/categories/pentecost.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:ancientla68@gmail.com"&gt;One Catholic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 07:37:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Beginning of the Catholic church</title><link>https://example.com/posts/beginning-of-the-catholic-church/</link><dc:creator>One Catholic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Beginning of the Catholic Church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Go therefore and make disciples of all nations"
.. TEASER_END
The Catholic Church traces its origin directly to Jesus Christ, who came into the world to preach the Kingdom of God and establish a community of believers united in faith, worship, and love. While many historical events shaped the Church as we know it, her true beginning lies in the life, death, and resurrection of Christ, and in the mission He entrusted to His Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christ Establishes His Church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus did not simply come to teach and leave behind written words. He formed a living community of disciples. He called the Twelve Apostles and gave them authority to teach, to heal, and to lead in His name. Among them, He gave a special role to Simon Peter, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"You are Peter, and on this rock I will build my Church, and the gates of Hades shall not prevail against it." (Matthew 16:18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This moment marks the foundation of the Church: Christ builds it not on a book alone, but on a community led by Peter and the Apostles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pentecost: The Birth of the Church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visible beginning of the Church is often identified with the day of Pentecost (Acts 2). After Jesus’ Ascension, the Apostles gathered in prayer with Mary, awaiting the gift of the Holy Spirit. When the Spirit descended as tongues of fire, the Apostles began to preach boldly in many languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that day, about three thousand people were baptized and joined the community of believers. This is why Pentecost is often called the “birthday of the Church.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apostles Carry the Mission Forward&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Pentecost, the Apostles went out into the world to spread the Gospel. Peter preached in Jerusalem and later in Rome, where he became the first Bishop of Rome. Paul, though not one of the Twelve, was called by Christ and became a great missionary, founding Christian communities throughout the Roman Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through their witness, the faith spread quickly. Despite persecution, the Church grew, rooted in the teaching of the Apostles and the celebration of the Eucharist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church Today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these humble beginnings, the Catholic Church has grown into a worldwide family of more than a billion members. Yet she remains the same Church founded by Christ, built upon the Apostles, and sustained by the Holy Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catechism of the Catholic Church reminds us:
"The Church is apostolic. It is built on a lasting foundation: ‘the twelve apostles of the Lamb’ (Rev 21:14). It is indestructible (cf. Mt 16:18). It is upheld infallibly in the truth: Christ governs her through Peter and the other apostles, who are present in their successors, the Pope and the college of bishops." (CCC 869)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church began with Christ Himself, took visible form at Pentecost, and has endured through history by the grace of God. For every Catholic, knowing the Church’s beginning is not only a matter of history but a reminder of our own calling: to live as witnesses of the Gospel in our time, just as the Apostles did in theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Go therefore and make disciples of all nations." (Matthew 28:19)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pentecost</category><guid>https://example.com/posts/beginning-of-the-catholic-church/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 06:04:05 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>